Stay real good.
Good morning.
Hope you all are doing well this morning.
Just as we were singing together, I just was reminded of how our passage is going to end this morning.
In Ephesians chapter 5, it says,
Speaking to one another in psalms, hymns, and spiritual songs, singing and making a melody with your heart to the Lord.
Always giving thanks for all the things in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, to God, even the Father.
And be subject to one another in the fear of Christ.
We're going to talk a lot about our identity in Christ this morning.
Paul's section here in Ephesians 4 and 5 is all about how we walk in the new identity of our new humanity.
And I don't think it's an accident that he ends with speaking to one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs and making a melody to the Lord.
It's an identity-forming activity.
And if you didn't grow up in the church or if you've never really worshipped in a congregation before, it can be confusing and weird.
But there's a reason why the Lord commands us to do this.
We're filled all day long, all week long, with things that shape our identity.
With activities that form us into the type of people that oppose the kingdom of God on earth as it is in heaven.
And so when we come and we sing things like,
The rain comes and the wind blows, but our house is built on you.
It's a corporate reminder to all of us that many of us are suffering in this room.
That many of us are experiencing the rain and the wind and the storm.
And yet we remind ourselves of what is true, not just what we can feel or experience,
but this apocalyptic, this revelation of what God has done in Christ to raise us above the powers and principalities
and see us with him in the heavenly places.
And so even when we can't see it, we can sing things like,
My house is built on you.
And this wind and this storm and this rain, it is going to come.
It will keep coming.
But we remind ourselves through songs and through Scripture,
corporately and individually,
that what we can see is not the only reality that exists.
And what we can see is a temporary reality compared to the reality of where we are headed.
That was not in the notes.
So now I have to get back to my notes somehow.
Um, we've been in the book of Ephesians.
I find it really helpful to cover books of the Bible in large sections
so that we don't lose sight of what the author is intending for his original audience.
And I hope that we have, um, Paul's kind of framework in mind.
I'd love to throw up that slide from a couple of weeks ago
because I think it articulates what Paul is doing in Ephesians
and in many other of his New Testament letters
is that, um, he is reminding us that we have been born into a temporary identity
that is influenced by the powers and principalities of this world.
The enemies of God that seek to divide people based on fear.
We see that, um, face with the sweat on the brow.
This is Genesis chapter three.
That from, uh, from the fall of God's good creation,
that we are, um, we are afraid and that we are anxious
and it forces us to divide into different categories,
different ethnicities, different identity markers.
And we view each other as enemies
because we feel like there isn't an abundant resource
and that we don't have a loving father
who wants to take care of us and give us good gifts.
And so we fight and we strive and we work
and we try and get what God has given us freely on our own merit.
And it divides us and it leads us down a path of death and destruction.
And this was the enemy's plan all along.
And we said that they thought getting Jesus to the cross
was them having their ultimate victory over God,
separating God's good design forever.
But what we have seen is that it is the manifold wisdom of God
to display to the powers and principalities of this world
that Jesus has conquered.
That the victory has been inaugurated
and that it will be consummated.
And the church now exists as the working model of new creation
on earth until he returns.
That we no longer have to live in fear.
We no longer have to live separated from our brothers and sisters, our neighbors.
We no longer have to view people who don't look like us as our enemies.
But we can live with an open hand and a full heart
and we can believe what is actually true.
And that is that we have a loving father
who owns a thousand cattle on a hill.
That we don't have to be afraid.
That we can live and surrender to him.
That we can trust in his provision.
This is what Paul has been doing in Ephesians chapter 1 through 3.
And as we turn to 4, he starts focusing in on what it looks like
for the church to live in that identity, to live in that reality.
And last week he said it looks like a group of diverse people
from all of these tribes and languages and tongues and identity markers
working together in their unique gifting
in such a way that leads to all of our maturity.
Because an immature church doesn't do much to show the powers and principalities
or the world outside of our walls that we are the working model of new creation.
We need to grow in maturity so that our witness becomes more visible to the watching world.
And he's going to continue to zoom into that fact this week
and talk a little bit more in specific terms
about what maturity looks like for believers in the church.
And if you have a bulletin, I do have notes on the back.
And what those notes are essentially is we're going to kind of zoom in
to these two circles here and talk about what are the specific behavior
and identity markers of kind of the old humanity and the new humanity
is what we're going to see.
I should have walked over to your side.
I always walk over to this side.
You guys never get any love over here.
I'm so sorry.
All right.
So we're going to zoom in over here to these two circles of reality
and talk about what it looks like for us to mature into the image of people
that are like Jesus, that function as if heaven has already come to earth.
Sound good?
We are going to take communion at the end.
If you haven't had a time to get a communion cup in the back
and you want to do that, feel free to do that at some point during the message.
Even if you have to fake a bathroom visit, that's fine.
And also before I pray, I do just want to remind you guys about the two services at Easter.
We're doing that to make room for people that typically like to visit churches on Easter.
And we also know that your friends, your family, people that you work with
will say yes to an invitation to go to church on Easter,
more likely than they will on a random Sunday in March.
And so please take advantage of that opportunity.
Be praying about who God might want you to invite to church to come with you.
And those of you that serve, we'd love for you to serve one and stay for one
so that we have enough volunteers to provide hospitality to hopefully a number of guests.
Sound good?
All right.
Let's pray.
Father in heaven, we are so grateful for another opportunity to gather with the saints
and in some mysterious way, gather with this great cloud of witnesses that have gone before us.
Those who have persevered hardship and difficulty.
Those who have run the race with endurance.
Who find their rest in your presence.
God, we're so grateful to gather with other believers and remind each other of what our identity is
through psalms, hymns, and spiritual songs.
I pray that as we open your word, that we would have eyes to see what you want us to see
and ears to hear what you want us to hear.
God, that this church would be maturing into the image of Jesus
so that we can demonstrate to our community around us what the kingdom of God looks like on earth until you return.
For your glory, for our good, and for the good of our neighbors.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
We're going to cover a big chunk this morning, and I'm going to try and get through it all without confusing you.
I've been confused all week because there's just a lot, but hopefully, Holy Spirit, you are welcome here.
Give us clarity and wisdom.
We're going to cover 417 through 521.
So if you want to follow along with me, that's where I'm going to be.
I am someone that I, the term that I give myself is that I'm like decent at a lot of things and not really great at anything.
Anybody feel like that's them?
Am I the only person in the room?
And part of the reason that I feel like that is true is because I teach, I've taught myself a lot of the things that I know,
which typically isn't the best approach, especially for me, apparently.
Two things that I've taught myself are how to play the piano and how to play golf.
Which means that I am very subpar at both of these activities.
But what it does mean is that sometimes I can play a few, like I could sit down at the piano.
I'm not going to, but I could.
I could sit down at the piano.
I could play a few basic songs with very bad technique.
And when I go out to the golf course, if any of you have ever been out there with me, I'll hit a few good shots.
I'll do it.
I will also hit plenty of very bad shots.
And the reality is, in order for me to have the identity of a golfer or a pianist, there is no amount of tweaking that I can do on my own that will make me a golfer or a pianist.
I've taught myself all of these bad habits.
I have all of this bad stuff going on in my head.
And so I could tweak all day long.
And I do.
Especially with golf.
I don't tweak with piano as much anymore.
I've given up.
But I could tweak with golf all day long, and I'm never going to be a golfer.
What needs to happen in order for me to have the identity of a pianist or a golfer is I actually have to submit myself to somebody who is a master of the trade.
I have to let them kill all of my old bad habits, take away everything that I have taught myself, and I have to learn a whole new way of doing the thing.
And I share that story with you because as we turn to some of the moral teachings of Paul in Ephesians chapter 4 and 5, as I think sometimes we rip some of the moral teachings in the New Testament out of context, and the application just becomes make some tweaks to your behavior.
And oftentimes Christianity becomes about just making ourselves a little bit better at certain behaviors.
And we study these passages, and we talk about gossip, and we talk about sexual impurity, and we talk about evil desires, and we just look at our lives, and we feel guilt and shame about all the ways in which we are living these sins out, and we just say, I'm just going to do better.
I'm going to sin less.
And the reality is any of us in the room who have tried that for any period of time at all would tell you, we will testify to you that it does not work.
And Paul isn't arguing here for self-taught tweaks on moral behavior.
He's inviting you to die to your old way of living, to die to your life that is underneath the powers and principalities of this earth, and to be raised and seated with Christ in the heavenly places, and to learn the patterns of behavior that Jesus shows us, not through hard work, but through faith and trust in him.
And if you were taught that the gospel is that Jesus died to forgive your sins, now that you are forgiven, you need to start obeying him out of gratitude for his sacrifice.
You learned a true but oversimplified message that often leads us to religious activity rather than a renewed mind and a resurrected heart.
And so Paul's entire argument here, if you have eyes to, if you look for it, we're actually going to read it all in one big chunk.
And if you look for it, you're going to see that Paul's argument is actually rooted in the Genesis account.
He's a good Pharisee, right?
He knows his Old Testament.
He's not making up some kind of new theology.
He's rooting his theology of the new humanity and what happened on the first few pages of Scripture.
He talks about darkness and light.
Sound like Genesis?
He talks about truth and deception.
Genesis?
He talks about foolishness and wisdom.
He talks about what it looks like to live under God's definition of wisdom and what it looks like to take from God the ability and the opportunity to divine good and evil for ourselves.
This whole argument that Paul has is rooted in old humanity and new humanity.
He is not saying you have to do less sin and do more obedience.
He's saying you have to die to your former way of living that was deceived by the powers and principalities and led you to disordered desires that led you to sinful habits that lead to death, chaos, and destruction.
And you have to be resurrected to new life in Christ.
And you have to walk in obedience with him by faith.
I love how Tim Mackey says it.
He says, the moral exhortations are grounded in the new humanity.
These moral exhortations are not behavior modifications.
They are identity markers of us becoming a new human.
Now, we don't have time to unpack 50 verses line by line.
And so what I want to do is just read this entire passage with that framework in our mind.
And hopefully we'll be able to kind of follow Paul's flow of thought.
And then I'll come back and do some high-level observations with the rest of our time.
Sound good?
All right.
Ephesians 4, verse 17.
So this I say and affirm together with the Lord that you walk no longer as the Gentiles walk in the futility of their mind, being darkened in their understanding.
Excluded from the life of God.
Sound like the garden?
See it?
All right.
Excluded from...
I lost my place.
I got to stop doing that.
Excluded from the life of God because of the ignorance that is in them, because of their hardness of heart.
They have become callous, having given themselves over to sensuality for the practice of every kind of impurity with greediness.
But you did not learn Christ in this way.
If indeed you have heard him and have been taught him, just as truth is in Jesus, that in reference to your former manner of life, you lay aside your old way of being.
Which is being corrupted in accordance with the lusts of deceit.
Deceit?
Anybody?
If you guys got highlighters or pens, go for it.
And that you be renewed in the spirit of your mind.
You put on the new self, which is in the likeness of God and has been created in righteousness and holiness and truth.
Therefore, laying aside falsehood, speak the truth to each other.
Speak the truth, each one of you, to his neighbor, for we are members of one another.
We've been brought into this church, this new family of God.
Be angry and do not sin.
Do not let the sun go down on your anger.
Do not give the devil an opportunity to deceive you.
He who steals must steal no longer.
But rather, he must labor, performing with his own hands what is good, so that we will have something to share with the one who is in need.
Let no unwholesome word proceed from your mouth, but only such is good for edification, according to the need for the moment, so that it will give grace to those who hear.
Do not grieve the Holy Spirit of God, by whom you were sealed for the day of redemption.
Let all bitterness, wrath, anger, clamor, and slander be put away from you, along with all malice.
Be kind to one another, tenderhearted, forgiving one another, just as God and Christ has forgiven you.
Key phrase here in 5, 1 and 2.
Therefore, be imitators of God.
As beloved children, new identity has been given to you.
As beloved children, walk in love, just as Christ also loved you and gave himself up for us as an offering, a sacrifice to God, a fragrant aroma.
But immorality, impurity, greed must not even be named among you, as is proper among the saints.
And there must be no filthiness or silly talk or coarse jesting, got it, which are not fitting, but rather giving thanks.
For this you know with certainty that no immoral or impure person or covetous man who is an idolater has an inheritance in the kingdom of Christ and God.
Let no one deceive you with empty words.
For because of these things, the wrath of God comes upon the sons of disobedience.
Therefore, do not be partakers with them.
For you were formerly darkness, but now you are the light in the Lord.
Walk as children of light.
That is your new identity for fruit.
For the fruit of the light consists in all goodness and righteousness and truth.
Trying to learn what is pleasing to the Lord.
Do not participate in unfruitful deeds in the darkness.
Instead, expose them.
For it is disgraceful even to speak of these things which are done by them in secret.
But all things become visible when they are exposed by the light.
For everything becomes visible in the light.
For this reason, it says, and many scholars believe that this is an early New Testament hymn rooted in Scripture.
These are the songs that they are singing to one another to remind themselves of their identity.
Awake, sleeper, arise from the dead, and Christ will shine on you.
Therefore, be careful how you walk, not as unwise, but as wise, making the most of your time because the days are evil.
So then, do not be foolish, but understand what the will of the Lord is.
Do not be drunk with wine, for that is dissipation, but be filled with the Spirit, speaking to one another in psalms and hymns and spiritual songs,
singing and making a melody with your heart to the Lord, always giving thanks for all things in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ.
To God, even the Father, and be subject to one another in reverence to Christ.
This is the word of the Lord.
Let's try that again.
Thanks be to God, all right?
You got it?
This is the word of the Lord.
There we go.
All right, so hopefully we can begin to see Paul's flow of thought that's rooted in this Genesis account, right?
There's darkness and light.
There's deceit and truth.
There's wisdom that is defined by God and wisdom that is defined by the old humanity,
where we take from God the fruit of the knowledge of good and evil,
and we begin to define wisdom for ourselves in our own image.
And he roots this whole argument in two overarching worldviews,
or two ways of existing in the world.
He says the old humanity and the new humanity.
The old humanity is animated by deception of the enemy.
We've already covered this.
It darkens our minds.
It hardens our hearts, and it leads us to selfish, dehumanizing, and destructive behaviors.
Deception from the enemy is what the old humanity is rooted in.
It leads to disordered desires that cause us to sin in our words, in our possessions, and in our body.
And yet the new humanity is animated by the truth of Christ.
It reorders our disordered desires slowly by the power of the Holy Spirit at work in us.
It leads us to a life of selfless, grateful, life-giving behaviors that lead to life and flourishing.
One is outside of the Garden of Eden, and the other is looking forward to the restored Eden when Christ returns.
This is all of what Paul is saying here in this passage.
And the key is that faith unlocks a new way of seeing reality.
The old way is the sweat of the brow.
We're concerned that we're not going to have enough, that there isn't enough, that we're on our own.
And the new way is filled with joy and gratitude and thanksgiving, that we have a loving Father who possesses all things, and there is abundance for all, and we can trust Him.
Even when we can't see it, we can believe that He has our best interest in mind.
This is faith in a new way to view reality.
Tim Mackey calls it apocalyptic living versus post or pre-apocalyptic living.
This, God has ripped open the curtain of what reality actually is.
And by faith, we see a new way to live.
And it's important here that we remember the language around response to the gospel, right?
In the Greek, repent literally means to turn around.
We're walking in the old humanity, led by deception that leads to disorder, desires, and sinful patterns of behavior that leads us to death and destruction and chaos.
And when we hear the gospel, we repent, we turn around, and we look towards the new humanity that is found in Christ.
And we walk in a different direction.
Repent means to turn around.
Faith is less like an intellectual agreement and more like surrender that leads to allegiance.
Paul's argument is that we have to die to our former way of being human and be raised with Christ to a new humanity.
Many scholars, when they read Paul's language of put off and put on, put off the old humanity, put on the new humanity,
they believe that it's rooted in this early church practice of baptism.
That when the early believers would get baptized, they would take off their old clothes and they would put on a white robe.
They would be baptized into the church, into this new family of God.
They would die to their old self and they would be raised to new life in Jesus.
And it's almost like Paul is reminding the Ephesian believers of what their new identity is after they have repented and believed,
put their faith and trust and been baptized into the family of God.
You no longer are that old person.
You put that way of thinking behind you and you put on a new identity that is rooted in truth that leads to reordered desires and righteousness in your actions and activities.
Christianity is not about changing our behaviors, but about being with and becoming like the only true human, Jesus Christ.
Jesus lived a perfect new humanity for us.
And he has invited us to die with him, to be raised to new life and to come under his discipleship and to follow his way of being.
And it's also important here that we remember because sometimes our translations don't do it for us,
that this is not an individual identity, but a communal one.
Paul's language here continues to be plural.
Paul's focus on diverse unity that leads to maturity from last week continues throughout this passage.
And he's saying that we do not learn Christ in isolation.
You and your Bible and the Holy Spirit are great, but there is something about living in community with other brothers and sisters in Christ where they point out your blind spots and they say,
this behavior that you are living in is not like Jesus.
And you're like, what behavior?
I don't know what you're talking about.
I'm great.
We need to live out this identity in community with one another.
Paul says that deception leads to disordered desires and sinful behavior.
And it's important to also notice that almost all of the behaviors that Paul talks about are unity-killing behaviors.
He's addressing a corporate congregation who he's just said, I need you to live in unity in the midst of diversity that leads to maturity.
And let me tell you all of the behaviors that will kill the unity that I've just asked you to live in.
And the truth of Christ will result in reordered desires, resulting in righteousness that leads to unity and diversity.
So he roots this argument in old humanity, new humanity.
And then he goes on to talk about the behaviors, the fruit of new humanity and the fruitlessness of old humanity.
You guys saw it when I read it.
There's a long list of sinful behaviors in this passage.
And I don't have time to cover them all, but I do think we can categorize them with these three overarching titles, right?
Like sin with our words, sin with our bodies, and sin with our possessions.
Pretty much all of the sinful actions that Paul lists are in some way, shape, or form find themselves under that category.
And again, in the middle of his argument, he roots it in our, in our identity in Jesus, in Ephesians chapter five, therefore be imitators of God as beloved children, walk and love just as Christ has loved you and gave himself for you.
As an offering and a sacrifice to God as a fragrant aroma.
All of this talk about behavior is rooted in us coming under Jesus.
I grew up with the WWJD bracelets.
Anybody else?
Great bracelets.
Awesome.
I have nothing against them.
Probably the better way to put it, since you are not a first century Jewish rabbi who's homeless, right?
Some of the things Jesus did, maybe you shouldn't do, like as a father or a wife or whatever, like Jesus had some freedoms that you didn't have being homeless and not having a family.
And so I think the better term here would be, what would Jesus do if he were you?
That is the, the, the key to opening up the door to the new humanity.
What would Jesus do if he were me in this situation?
And I've, I've seen a, a, a, a social media image flying around.
What would Jesus do?
He'd flip tables.
Let's just, let's not.
He flipped tables twice and it wasn't about, anyway.
All right.
Let's just like, let's flip the tables in our own lives.
I stole that line from my wife.
Let's flip the tables of our own sin before we start flipping the tables of other people's sin.
Let's like, let's, let's clean the house inside before we start pointing fingers at those outside.
What would Jesus do if he were me in this situation?
And like, really like ponder the life and teachings of Jesus.
Ponder the crucifixion.
Typically what Jesus would do if he were you is he would die to his selfish, he would have you die to your selfish desires and live with generosity towards those who are your enemies.
That's not what we like to say when we like to say, what would Jesus do?
We pick the things that we like about Jesus's life and we apply them out of context to do the thing that we actually want to do.
And that is not the new humanity.
All right.
Words.
We sin with our words, slander, gossip, obscene joking, and foolish talk.
They create self-righteousness by dehumanizing others in order to make ourselves feel better.
This is sweat of the brow behavior.
This is viewing other people as less valuable than ourselves.
And so we use our words to tear other people down and to lift ourselves up.
And I talk for a living.
So you might guess that I am really bad at this.
Maybe you guys are quiet.
Like you thought I was not bad at it.
I'm very bad at it.
This is a, this is a challenge for me.
And this week has caused me to reevaluate what it is that leads me to gossip and slander and obscene joking.
Because I was discipled in the middle school boys locker room.
So I know how to make an obscene joke.
And what it is, is it's this old humanity way of thinking.
It's, I am more valuable than somebody else and they are in my way.
And I'm going to tear them down with my words and build myself up.
I'm going to give myself the, the satisfaction.
I want other people to think great of me and other people to think poorly of this person.
It's old humanity.
Literally, I was, I was studying this passage.
Can I, can I confess to you all?
Can you, will you receive my confession?
Okay.
Studying this passage.
Focused on the words.
Part of it in my study, get in my car, go to the gas station.
I pull around.
I'm going straight.
There's a car coming this way to turn left.
And there's one gas pump and we're like coming here.
And I'm like, I can't, she doesn't have her blinker on.
I don't know if she's going to the gas pump or not.
And technically I think I have the right of way.
So I pull into the gas pump and luckily the person in front of me pulls out.
So I pull up to the second gas pump.
She comes in behind me.
I get out of the car.
I walk up to her cause I'm a good pastor who was just studying this passage.
And I say, I didn't know if you were coming to the pump or not.
I wasn't trying to steal the pump from you.
And she gives me like a brother, sister.
Old humanity comes out immediately.
I'm like, how dare you?
I'm being kind.
I went out of my way to tell you that.
Right.
And as soon as like, it's in my heart and I'm like, that is, that is old humanity.
That is, I'm better than her.
She's my enemy.
I need her to be down so that I can be up.
And this is what we do with our speech.
We dehumanize other people.
We put people into categories that are other than us.
And Paul says, instead, speak the truth in love and use your words for encouragement that
builds others up.
This is the new humanity.
And here's the deal.
Sometimes, self-righteousness coming out in me.
Sometimes the jokes that I make and the gossip that I participate in are exposing injustice
and bad things in the world.
Paul isn't saying that you can't participate in exposing injustice.
He isn't saying that you can't speak the truth in love to situations that are hurting other
people.
He's just saying that gossip and slander and cruel joking is not the way to go about it.
And it's so much easier for me to just make a joke about somebody that I disagree with
than to actually go to them and love and say, let's have a conversation.
And oftentimes, we're not in a position where we can go to the person and have a conversation.
And so guess what we do then, brother and sister?
We pray.
If we can't talk, we pray.
We do not gossip.
We do not slander.
We do not make foolish, obscene jokes.
And the most common place I see this in our current cultural moment is in the political
sphere.
We group people into categories based on their ideological beliefs.
We distance ourselves from them because they disagree with us.
We dehumanize them so that we don't feel bad about making cruel jokes or saying evil things.
And it ruins unity and escalates the discourse.
And it has no place in the people of God.
And honestly, I'm sick of opening up my Facebook profile to see my timeline full of Christians
posting or reposting dehumanizing rhetoric around political identities.
If you have an issue with someone, go to them.
And if you can't, pray for them.
And if you have to make your opinion known, social media is probably not the place to do
that.
But if the Lord, through the Holy Spirit, says you need to make your opinion known on social
media, there's a way to do it that is speaking the truth and love and edifying the people around
you.
We do not wrestle against flesh and blood.
That person and the other political party from you is not your enemy.
They are a neighbor for you to love.
In the new humanity, people you disagree with are not your enemies to defeat.
They are your neighbors to love.
And I can't help but think how much different our political climate would be if every Christian
in America put off the old humanity way of speaking and put on the new humanity of speaking
the truth and love and encouraging one another.
The breath in your lungs is a gift from God.
New humanity knows that.
And they speak differently because of it.
Possessions.
Running late.
The old humanity is about survival and temporary pleasure.
And so the way that we view our possessions when we're in this mindset, it's all about us getting
the things that we want, even if it's at the state, even if it's at the expense of others.
It leads to entitlement and to envy, which can cause us to steal in order to get what we want.
Now, most of us in the room probably don't do what we would typically think of as stealing,
but we are envious of our neighbor.
We find dishonest and dehumanizing ways to make more money, to climb the ladder at work,
to hoard possessions while others around us don't have what they need.
And in contrast, the new humanity is about abundance and flourishing for everyone.
New humans should be honest and work hard to contribute to the flourishing of the world
around us.
Their vocation is to be generous with what they have.
Paul's saying here, old humanity hoards and stores and steals, does whatever they can to get ahead.
New humanity says everything is a gift from God, and I'm going to steward it like that.
That is the case.
New humans know that everything we have is a gift, and it should be used for the good of others.
Lastly, Paul goes on to address what we do with our bodies.
He says, the old humanity is obsessed with temporary pleasure.
Sexual immorality is taking a gift that God has given, and it is turning it into a God.
It is worshiping creation rather than the creator.
We put no limits on our physical appetites.
We overeat, we consume alcohol in abundance, and we put no boundaries on our sexual desires.
We dehumanize people through our lustful thoughts, pornography, and sexual activity outside of the self-giving covenant of marriage.
Sexual immorality views our neighbor not as a person to be loved, but a person to be used for our own temporary pleasure.
And this is why we have problems overcoming our lustful thoughts, overcoming our evil desires, is because we don't view it as an old mindset.
We just try and grit our fists down and say, I'm not going to lust anymore.
That's not what Paul's saying.
Paul's saying is, lust comes from this deception from the enemy that says that your personal pleasure is more important than the neighbor that you're lusting after.
And Paul says, if you want to be changed from the inside out, you have to allow Christ to renew your mind.
The new humanity is filled with gratitude and thanksgiving for the good gifts of God.
We trust the boundaries that God has placed around food and alcohol and sex because he is a good father who loves us and wants good gifts for us and everyone around us.
New humanity people believe that we are not our own and that we are bought with a price.
Therefore, we choose to use our bodies in a way that leads to life and flourishing that God desires for his creation.
It's about putting off the lie that leads to the disordered desire that makes you sin.
And that sin leads to death and not just physical death, but just chaos in the situations of life.
I'm certain that pretty much everyone in this room has been drug into a situation that felt like death because of somebody else's sexual immorality or our own.
It's just the old humanity leading us down a path of destruction.
In the moment, all we can think about is temporary pleasure.
But Paul says, we need new minds that are surrendered to Jesus.
We need to repent and walk away from the old way of believing and we need to believe the truth.
And this is in every category, words, possessions, body.
It's all, anytime we're sinning, it's because we're believing a lie.
It's because we've been deceived by the enemy of God.
We've been drug out of the light and back into the darkness and the enemy has a foothold in our life.
And the response is not stop sinning.
The response is stop believing the lie and walk back to who Christ made you to be.
All of this gets really gnarly if we're honest.
And I don't know about you, but I know that people, it seems like the church in America today, we don't like to talk about wrath.
I don't like to talk about wrath.
Maybe I'll take it off of you guys and put it on me.
I think one of the reasons we don't like to talk about wrath is because it's often misunderstood.
Paul breaks here to remind us of the consequences of the old humanity.
The old humanity is leading to death and destruction outside of the garden.
And even as we embrace our new humanity, there will be people who are trying to deceive us with empty words.
They'll try to say this whole Jesus resurrected from the dead.
And so you have a new humanity is crazy talk.
Just do what everybody else is doing.
Radical generosity.
That's ridiculous.
Sexual purity, sexual boundaries, foolishness.
They will try and deceive us.
And Paul reminds us here, don't be deceived because the consequences of being deceived is God's wrath.
And again, wrath is often misunderstood and misapplied as an angry and vengeful God punishing sinful humanity.
But Paul in Romans will go on for a whole chapter to redefine what he means by God's wrath.
And what Paul means by God's wrath is that we have a loving father who is letting his rebellious children suffer the consequences of their own decisions.
We have a loving father who is begging us to stay with him and trust him.
But when we refuse, when we reject him, when we walk away from him, he's not going to force us to obey.
He's going to allow us to walk away and he's going to allow us to experience the consequences of our decisions.
That is the wrath of God.
All over Romans, the wrath of God is he let them have what they wanted.
Meanwhile, he's like the father of the prodigal son waiting on the porch for one ounce of repentance so that he can run after you.
God's final word is not his wrath, but his mercy.
And the gospel shouts to us that God loves us and has made a way for us to escape the lies of the enemy that destroy us.
And he has made a way for us to experience the new humanity that leads to life and flourishing.
Paul continues his argument with two different illustrations that build out his argument.
He's a good preacher here.
We don't have to rehash all of it because he's using the same illustration to make the same or two different illustrations to make similar points.
He says the old humanity is like darkness where fruit cannot grow.
And the new humanity is like light where the fruit flourishes and grows.
The old humanity leads to foolish actions while the new humanity is rooted in wisdom.
Again, echoes of the story of creation and the fall.
We've been ripped out of the fruitful garden and we've pushed ourselves into darkness.
We've been ripped out of the place where God is allowed to define what wisdom is.
And we have been put, we've put ourselves in the place of God and we've begun to define what wisdom is.
And our wisdom is foolishness.
And he goes on and one last phrase I want to point out just because I think it's too good to pass up.
And then I can't find it because this is a different Bible than I normally read.
Where's, what verse is making the most of your time?
Somebody help me.
Oh, there it is.
16.
Thank you.
Therefore, be careful how you walk, not as unwise, but as wise, making the most of your time because the days are evil.
And I don't know how you've read that in the past, but when I read that, I often think like, oh, I got to steward my calendar well.
Right?
I got a limited amount of time.
I got to make sure I'm efficient with how I use it.
Again, it becomes this legalistic practice.
It becomes this religious duty thing.
And Tim Mackey makes the argument that the language works better when you read it like liberating your time.
It's the word for redemption, it's the word for redemption, for being bought back.
Essentially, the argument is the old humanity is in bondage under the temporary nature of fallen creation.
All we can, all we can, all the old humanity can see is the 70 to 100 years that we have here on earth.
And so we use our time and we use our time and our energy and our resources to try and suck out as much life and flourishing as we can for this short amount of time.
Paul says the new humanity, their time has been liberated because we now get to live in light of eternity.
We now get to view all of our time as a gift from God that we can use for his purposes that lead to life and flourishing.
And then Paul transitions to the singing and reading and encouraging one another.
Again, it's all about reminding ourselves of our identity in Christ.
It's identity forming behaviors.
And I cannot stress enough that whether you know it or not, your life Monday through Saturday is filled with identity shaping behaviors.
The enemy of God is trying to shape your identity back into the old humanity all week long.
It's the reason that we sing with one another.
It's the reason that we do life with one another outside of these walls because we have to remind ourselves that what we've been deceived to believe is not true, but the truth is found in Christ.
We need to allow him to renew our minds.
I know this was a lot to cover in a short amount of time, and I am certain that I did not do it justice.
But I hope that we can walk away seeing that Paul's argument here isn't about changing our behavior,
but about being born again into a totally new kind of human.
And maybe you're listening to this, and you've been trying to tweak your moral behaviors, but it hasn't been working.
Or it feels like one step forward and two steps backward.
Maybe you've only understood the gospel to be an individual spiritual transaction between you and God that just primarily impacts your eternal destiny.
Maybe you're here, you've never felt like you needed Jesus to be a good person.
Right?
I hear that a lot.
I can be a good person without Jesus.
Maybe you understand all of this, but you're being deceived by the powers and principalities.
You've been lured out of the light and back into the darkness.
I don't know where you sit when you receive this, but the reality is the invitational response to all of those categories and ones that I haven't mentioned is the same.
The invitation is to come and die.
This is when people typically walk away from Jesus after a couple of miracles.
They're like, this guy's awesome.
And he says, come and die.
That's the response that Paul is inviting us to today.
Come and die.
Die to the old ways of being human.
The humanity rooted in deception that leads to disordered desires and sin and results in death.
Come to Jesus.
Let the one who was raised resurrect you into a totally new way of being human.
Rooted in truth about God's good world.
Let the new reality reorder your desires in a way that leads to righteousness and results in life and flourishing, not just for yourself, but for everyone around you.
Imagine how much more effective the church would be at embodying the kingdom of God on earth until Christ returns if each one of us had this mindset among us.
If we would speak the truth in love when we saw our brother and sister believing a lie from the enemy and acting in a behavior that is unbecoming for a child of God.
Church, this is my invitation for us.
That we would embrace our new identity in Christ.
And that we would do that in community with one another.
And that when I step out of line, have a conversation with me.
When you see a brother or sister in Christ step out in line, have a conversation with them.
Kill the gossip, the slander, the foolish, obscene joking.
Kill it all.
Surrender it to Jesus.
The impact that a group of people committed to this way of living could have on the world around them.
Let's pray.
Father in heaven, we thank you yet again for an opportunity to gather with the saints.
The imperfect, broken, and yet redeemed people of God.
Who have been invited to bring our gifts, to mature towards Christ, who is our head.
God, if there's anyone in this room who has yet to die to their old self.
Who has yet to repent of the lies that they have believed from the enemy and turned back to you.
If there's anyone in this room who has not yet put off the old way of living and put on the new way of living through baptism.
I pray this morning that today would be the day that you are inviting them.
That you are calling them out of their old humanity into a new humanity.
If there's anybody in this room who has been trying to become more like you through behavior modification.
God, may today be the day that you allow our minds to be renewed by the truth.
Through the power of your spirit.
Father, we love you.
We thank you for Jesus.
Amen.